Finding aid for the Barbara Morgan photographs LSC.1873
UCLA Library Special Collections
Barbara Morgan photographs
1928-1972
UCLA Library Special Collections
Morgan, Barbara Brooks, 1900-1992
LSC.1873
1 oversize_boxes
The collection contains nineteen mounted photos by Barbara Morgan, on subjects including dance, Camp Treetops, nature, and one from the Junkyard Series.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9966536073606533
Biography
Barbara Brooks Morgan was born in Buffalo, Kansas on July 8, 1900, but grew up in Los Angeles, CA. She attended UCLA from 1919 to 1923, and later joined the art faculty (1925-30). She married Willard D. Morgan (ca. 1925) and relocated to New York (1930). After the birth of her two sons, Douglas (1932) and Lloyd (1935), she began to concentrate on her photography career. An accomplished designer, author, artist, and photographer, she is best known for her photographs of American modern dancers, among them, Martha Graham, Doris Humphrey, Pearl Primus, Jose Limon, and Charles Weidman. She contributed articles and reviews to various publications and published several books including, Martha Graham: Sixteen Dances in Photographs (1941), Summer's Children: A Photographic Cycle of Life at Camp about Camp Treetops (1951), and A Collection of Material about Barbara Morgan (1972), as well as having a photo in Family of Man (1955). She died August 18, 1992 in Scarsdale, NY.
Scope and Content
The collection includes 19 mounted photos taken by Barbara Morgan. These photos include photos of dancers, nature, various portraits, one of Camp Treetops (a children's camp, featured in her book Summer's Children) and one from her junkyard series. There is one example of her experimental photomontages. The collection includes "Girl Playing Recorder," which was included in the 1955 book Family of Man.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Portraits
Dance
Auto Junkyard Series
Camp Treetops
Nature
Related Material
Collection about Barbara Morgan, 1960-1972. Collection 1112. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Barbara Morgan Wight Gallery Collection, 1938-1967. Collection 1872. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections.
Women artists.; Women photographers -- Archives.; Morgan, Barbara Brooks, 1900-1992
- Auto Junkyard Series, 1947
  - Resurrection in the Junkyard, Date Taken: 1947 Date Printed: 1969; 13 1/4" × 10 1/4" on 16" × 18" (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Scope and Contents note
    Photograph
- Camp Treetops (Summer's Children), 1947
  - Girl Playing Recorder, Date Taken: 1945; 9 5/8" × 13 3/16" on 15" × 20" (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Photograph (from "Summer's Children" and "Family of Man - MOMA), inscribed "For Annita Delano"
- Dance, 1938-1944
  - Martha Graham in "Letter to the World", Date Taken: 1940 Date Printed: 1971; 7 3/8" × 9 1/2" on 13" × 16" (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Photograph, Martha Graham seated on bench, inscribed "For Bertha Wardell"
  - Martha Graham in "Letter to the World" ("For Annita Delano"), Date Taken: 1940; 9 1/2" × 13 1/8" on 16 1/2" × 19 1/2" (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Photograph, Martha Graham's skirt forming arc, inscribed "For Annita Delano"
  - Valerie Bettis in "Desperate Heart", 10 3/4" × 12 1/2" on 18 1/2" × 20" (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Charles Weidman in "Lynchtown" (Humphrey-Weidman Group), Date Taken: 1938 Date Printed: 1969; 11 9/16" × 18 7/8" on 18" × 27: (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Jose Limon, "Peon" from "Mexican Suite", Date Printed: 1970; 13 1/4" × 17 7/8" on 21" × 26" (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Nature, 1943-1967
  - Walnut, Date Taken: 1943; 13" × 10 5/8" on 16" × 20" (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Ikons in Time-Stream (Hittite Mother Goddess 2000 BC + Empire State Bldg NYC 1938 AD), Date Taken: 1964 Date Printed: 1971; 17 3/4" × 13 1/2" on 26" × 20" (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Fossil in Formation, Date Taken: 1965 Date Printed: 1971; 17 1/2" × 13" on 24" × 20" (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Artificial Life From the Laboratory, Date Printed: 1971; 18 7/8" × 15" on 27" × 22" (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Beech Tree I, Date Taken: 1945 Date Printed: 1970; 13" × 17 1/4" on 21" × 27" (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Portraits, 1942-1958
  - Dr Diasetz Suzuki, Date Printed: 1969; 10 5/8" × 7" on 15"x 11 1/8" (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Portrait photograph
  - Dr Daisetz Suzuki (In Study) (in NYC during session of teaching at Columbia University), Date Taken: 1958; 10 3/4" × 9 1/2" on 16 1/2" × 19 1/2" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Gerald Heard, Date Printed: 1971; 12 3/4" × 10 5/8" on 20" × 16" (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Professor Joseph Campbell and Student, Sarah Lawrence college, Date Taken: 195- Date Printed: 1971; 12" × 9 1/2" on 18" × 14" (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Charles Sheeler and His Favorite Beech Tree, Date Printed: 1971; 9 7/8" × 12 1/2" on 16" × 20" (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Portrait photograph inscribed "Best Wishes to the Carneys."
  - Willard Morgan Tossing Cats (Strobe), Date Taken: 1942 Date Printed: 1971; 7 13/16" × 13 1/2" on 15" × 19 7/8" (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lloyd's Head, 9 1/16" × 13" on 16 5/8" × 21 1/4" (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Portrait photograph of Morgan's son